AMANDA CERCAS CURRY

amandacurry.github.io - amanda.cercas@gmail.com - www.linkedin.com/in/amanda-cercas-curry

My research interests are broad and range from the development of open-domain conversational systems to their social impact and how we can develop more ethical AI across disciplines. I believe a multi-disciplinary approach involving diverse teams and feminist design methods are key in solvina today's ethical and technical challenges.

EXPERIENCE

PhD Student in Computer Science: Heriot-Watt University (Edinburgh, UK), September 2016 -ongoing: My main areas of research are abuse detection and mitigation and ethical considerations in social dialogue systems. My project supervisors are Prof. Verena Rieser, and Prof. Ruth Aylett.

HEAD OF TECHNOLOGY: Ethical Intelligence (Edinburgh, UK), May 2019-August 2020: Think tank assessing and advising AI companies on ethical issues relating to data collection and algorithm usage.

TEACHING ASSISTANT: Heriot-Watt University (Edinburgh, UK), September 2016 – 2019 Assisted teaching in Software Development and Conversational Agents courses.

RESEARCH ASSISTANT: Heriot-Watt University (Edinburgh, UK), Summer 2014 and 2015: Developed an online game to evaluate how best to present uncertain information, such as weather reports, to the general public. Participated in Explorathon 2015, a public engagement event at the Edinburgh Zoo.

LEADERSHIP AND

Cohost of Let's Chat Ethics (2020 - ongoing): Weekly podcast covering **RESPONSIBILITIES** topics relating to Ethics and Al.

> Cohost of Building Ethical Intelligence (2020): Educational series including online workshops, webinars and podcasts on topics such as Emotion AI and anger, Racial Bias in Al.

Team Leader Amazon Alexa Prize 2018: Coordinated liaison between Amazon's support and the student team. Implemented several neural abuse detection models using AllenNLP and RasaNLU. The models were trained on manually-annotated data from the 2017 Prize. Implemented a Lucene-based retrieval bot that uses certain subreddits containing interesting facts and thoughts as a source of information.

Student Committee Member of SigGen (2018-2020): Involved in the everyday functioning of the group.

Cofounder and committee member of InterconnectHW: (2015-2016) A network for female students in STEM subjects in Scotland.

PRIZES AND AWARDS

NESTA Al For Good Grantee 2020 £40,000

Amazon Alexa Challenge Finalist 2018 \$50,000

Amazon Alexa Challenge Finalist 2017 \$50,000

James Watt PhD Scholarship 2016 Heriot-Watt University

8th BCSWomen Lovelace Colloquium 2015: First prize for final year undergraduate research.

Dean's List and Outstanding Student Scholarship 2010 Hunter College

EDUCATION

European Summer School in Language, Logic and Information (Bolzano, Italy) August 2016.

Machine Learning in NLP Summer School (Lisbon, Portugal), July 2016.

BSc Hons COMPUTER SCIENCE: Heriot-Watt University (Edinburgh, UK), June 2015

Achieved: 1st Class

<u>Dissertation:</u> Generating and Evaluating Context-Dependent Route Instructions in Virtual Environments.

<u>Courses include</u>: Artificial Intelligence, Data Mining and Machine learning, Biologically Inspired Computing, Data Visualisation and Analysis, Advanced Interaction Design, Intelligent Robotics.

BA LIBERAL ARTS: CUNY Hunter College (New York, USA), 2010-2011, GPA 4.0. Transferred to Heriot-Watt University.

BILINGUAL INTERNATIONAL BACCALAUREATE DIPLOMA: United Nations International School (New York, US), 2010

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Amanda Cercas Curry, Judy Robertson and Verena Rieser, 2020. Conversational Assistants and Gender Stereotypes: Public Perceptions and Desiderata for Voice Personas. In proceedings: Workshop on Gender Bias in NLP at COLING. Barcelona, Spain.

Amanda Cercas Curry and Verena Rieser, 2019. A Crowd-based Evaluation of Abuse Response Strategies in Conversational Agents. In proceedings: SigDial 2019. Stockholm, Sweden.

Amanda Cercas Curry, Ioannis Papaioannou, Alessandro Suglia, Shubham Agarwal, Igor Shalyminov, Xinnuo Xu, Ondrej Dusek, Arash Eshghi, Ioannis Konstas, Verena Rieser and Oliver Lemon, 2018. Alana v2: Entertaining and Informative Open-Domain Social Dialogue using Ontologies and Entity Linking. In proceedings: Amazon Alexa Prize 2018. Las Vegas, NV, USA.

Amanda Cercas Curry and Verena Rieser, 2018. #Me Too, Alexa: How Conversational Agents Respond to Sexual Harassment. In proceedings: NAACL 2018 Second Workshop on Ethics in NLP. New Orleans, LA, USA.

Ioannis Papaioannou, **Amanda Cercas Curry**, Jose L. Part, Igor Shalyminov, Xinnuo Xu, Yanchao Yu, Ondrej Dusek, Verena Rieser and Oliver Lemon, 2017. An Ensemble Model with Ranking for Social Dialogue. In proceedings: NIPS 2017 Workshop on Conversational Al. Long Beach, CA, USA.

Jekaterina Novikova, Ondřej Dušek, **Amanda Cercas Curry** and Verena Rieser, 2017. Why we need new evaluation metrics for NLG. In proceedings: EMNLP 2017, Copenhagen, Denmark.

SKILLS

TECHNICAL:

Prefered languages: Python, Java

Known technologies: Allen NLP, Pandas, Scikit-learn, IBM SPSS, R

LANGUAGES: English and Spanish (bilingual), German and French

(intermediate)